Guide to the Fanny Howe Papers, 1981-1995
Department of Special Collections
Howe, Fanny. Papers,
1981-1995
M0848
Howe, Fanny.
2.5 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Manuscripts, typescripts, and correspondence, the last including letters from Samuel Beckett, William Corbett, Mark Mirsky, and Alice Walker (one of Walker's containing reference to Tillie Olsen).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Acquisition Information
Purchased, 1996.
Biography
Fanny Howe is Professor of Writing and Literature at the University of California, San Diego. She is the author of more than twenty books of fiction and poetry, most recently, One Crossed Out, 1997.
Access Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Beckett, Samuel, 1906-; Corbett, William, 1942-; Mirsky, Mark.; Olsen, Tillie.; Walker, Alice, 1944-; American literature--20th century.
Collection Contents
- Series 1. Manuscripts and typescripts
  - O'clockFall 1995, Ring-bound, white wrappers, 90 pp. Fair copy, virtually, though ink corrections on two leaves at least (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Poems
  - Bronte Wilde: penultimate draft: corrected ts, n.d., 183 leaves, in rough order. Much paste up & corrected texts; some mechanically reproduced leaves (Box 1, Folder 2.124)
    Fiction
  - Saving history: summary treatment from the novel & corrected ts, n.d., 20 pp. summary treatment + 3 p. corrected ts. + 184 pp. corrected ts. + 1 leaf ms. (Box 1, Folder 3.134)
  - Poems in corrected typescript. [Folder is mislabeled "Travel"]n.d., 120 leaves, including a few prose pieces; draft of one letter; a few ms. leaves on ruled yellow foolscap. Much correction in ink throughout. (Box 1, Folder 4.147)
    Includes: Proposal for a collection of Essays, 1 p. -- Puella songs [completed Holy Week, 1994] -- Strand -- For Tom Raworth -- The only way
  - Inquest and experience: ts & ms, n.d., 13 leaves of ms on ruled yellow foolscap + 10 leaves ts., very heavily corrected throughout (Box 1, Folder 5.152)
    Includes: drafts of poems
  - Tis of thee: seven year project "to be performed with jazz in San Diego" [1 of 2]n.d. (Box 2, Folder 6.163)
  - Tis of thee: seven year project "to be performed with jazz in San Diego" [2 of 2]n.d. (Box 2, Folder 6.465)
  - Africa America: a love story: typescripts, cut up, pasted up. -- London, n.d., 54 leaves with short prose passages on recto & verso & 5 related pages (Box 2, Folder 7.173)
  - Fear: draft, 1993 Oct. 2, 64 sections, each section being (usually) 2 sheets taped together (Box 2, Folder 8.183)
    Includes corrected ts.
  - Miscellaneous short pieces1991-1992, 52 leaves, ts & ms, corrected ts. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Includes: The Netherworld -- Victory -- Latin -- Bad eyes
  - Prose work set in or near Boston with characters Ellen, Mason, and Blaise: drafts,n.d., 50 p. (Box 2, Folder 10.1104)
    This group may belong to "Fear". With related sheets beginning "What was the thing ... ", 18 p. Also includes related text: Premise, Jamaica Plain, 6 p., an important prose outline of the whole project.
  - The birth of error (from: The mother: a progress), n.d., 12 p., corrected ts. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Related to: Tis of thee, which is mentioned in passing.
  - Scraps and fragments related to Fear,n.d., 47 p., lightly corrected ts. (Box 2, Folder 12.1123)
  - Project with Maureen Owensn.d. (Box 2, Folder 13.1132)
    Includes: 2 tls from Maureen Owens, 1991 - 2 p. -- ALS from Bob Grenier, 2 p. -- 43 leaves (xeroxed) texts
  - Saving history n.d., 1 ms. leaf + 2 xeroxed sheets (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Be again: voiceover,n.d., 6 p., ts (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Text for voiceover for video filmed in Ireland.
  - Bronte Wilde: intermediate draft of new version [1 of 2]n.d., 170 leaves; some corrected, some pasted up (Box 2, Folder 16.1163)
  - Bronte Wilde: intermediate draft of new version [2 of 2]n.d., 170 leaves; some corrected, some pasted up (Box 3, Folder 16.4)
  - London notebook: ts, corrected, 1993-1994, 76 leaves (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Contents are autobiographical and include frequent correction in ink.
  - Manuscript notebook, Boston - UK1993-1994, 1 v.: brown cloth, gilt, ca. 5x7 in., signed + 12 leaves of mss/notes tipped in (Box 3, Folder 18.1182)
  - NOD [previously: October]: poems, corrected ts,1996 Jan. 15, 1 v. (93 p.): ringbound, blue wrappers. Notes on plain covers in ink. (Box 3, Folder 19.1194)
    Includes "mid-draft", ts, velo-bound in yellow wrappers and later draft, 134 p., ts, very few marks
  - SALT: middle draft,n.d., 118 leaves; corrected ts., with yellow post-it tabs (Box 3, Folder 20.1204)
    Internal title: The Children's progress from the dream world to the world which is delivered under the likeness of a dream. Includes additional version, London, n.d., 129 leaves, no corrections, but at least one paste-on.
  - Manuscript notebook accompanying SALT typescriptsn.d., ringbound, blue illus. covers. 152 p. closely written holograph ink (Box 4, Folder 21)
    Includes creative text.
- Series 2. Correspondence with established authors
  - Beckett, Samuel. ANS to Mary, Paris, 1981 Sept. 11, 1 ans + envelope (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Letter offers sympathy to Mary for difficult times which she is experiencing.
  - Beckett, Samuel. ANS to Fanny Howe, Paris, 1981 Sept. 11, 1 ans + envelope (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Letter expresses sympathy to Fanny Howe on behalf of Mary for difficult times that Mary is experiencing. Indicates that he does not have Mary's address.
  - Corbett, William. Poet1993 - 1995, 11 als + 11 acs (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Mirsky, Mark. Novelist1992 - 1994, 7 tls + 63 p., typed texts (Box 4, Folder 4.142)
  - Walker, Alice1983 - 1987, n.d., 10 als + 1 tls (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Includes letters beginning on the day after Walker's 39th birthday. Letters relate to Walker's relationship with Robert, feelings for Howe's struggles for teaching and health, and on Tillie Olsen's meanness in tearing apart a Walker essay on Martin Luther King, Jr. she had sent to Olsen but which was returned "torn up".
- Series 3. Correspondence, general
  - Banks, Russell, 2 letters (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Browne, Laynie (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Codrescu, Andrei (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Cole, Peter (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Creeley, Robert - APC1993 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - d'Ormesson, Donatella, 2 letters (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Davis, Leslie (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Davison, Peter (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - deLissovoy, Peter. Author of FEEL GOOD1988-1991, 23 letters (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - EL1993 Sept. 30 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Foye, Raymond - APC (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Gams, John (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Green, Paul. UK publisher1995, 8 letters + 7 envelopes (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Greenfield, Amy (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Guest, Barbara (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Hambone [note: added to C27 - Nathaniel Mackey, same person] (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Hausman, Fredrik (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Hejinian, Lyn. Poet1986 - 1995, 8 letters + 1 postcard (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - High, John1992, 20 leaves (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Howe, Fanny to Peter Gizzi [retained copy] (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Johnston, Devin (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Kozberg, Joanne (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - L'Heureux, John (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Lee, Don, 2 letters (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Loren, Davi (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Lovell, Thoreau (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Mackey, Nathaniel (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Manson, Peter, 2 letters (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Mayer, Bernadette1994, 2 als (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Messerli, Douglas. Sun & Moon Press, 3 letters + signed agreement; proof cover (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Miles with peoms (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Morrow, Brad, 2 letters (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Mounkall, Stephen T. (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Muckle, John, 2 letters + Howe proofs + draft, Howe to Muckle (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - O'Sullivan, Maggie (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - O-BLEK (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Oerti, Katrin (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Ratner, Rochelle (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Rieselbach, Erik, 3 letters (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Sherman, Ken, 5 letters (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Stein, Jean (Grant Street), 4 letters (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Sukenik, Ron, 1 form letter (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Tannahill, Anne (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Tobier, Richard (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - Todd, Richard (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Treisman, Deborah (Box 4, Folder 46)
    Includes note on Grand Street xerox
  - Wheeler, Susan (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Woods, Peggy, 3 letters (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Xeroxed letters & copies forwarded, 30 p. (Box 4, Folder 49)
- Series 4. Manuscripts by others
  - Armantrout, Rae. Feminist politics and the meaning of clarity.n.d., 14 p. xeroxed prose essay, inscribed. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Fanny's tea: holograph poemn.d., 1 p. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Gander, Forest. Eggplants and lotus root.n.d., 11 p. typescript, inscribed (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Gander, Forest. Hopkins leap: typescriptn.d., 3 p. typescript, inscribed (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Grenier, Robertn.d., 16 leaves of text (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Rodefer, Stepehn. Moncanard1995, 1 v. (30 p.): initialed. No. 3 of 7. (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Walker, Alice. Coming in from the cold: speech draft,ca. 1984, 18 leaves, inscribed to Fanny Howe, mechanically reproduced, corrections revealed (Box 5, Folder 7)
    Draft of speech eventually given by Walker at the National Writers Union, New York City, 1984 Oct. 19.
- Series 5. Contracts and Agreements
  - Contracts and agreements of Fanny Howe, Includes contracts and agreements with: Avon (2); Museum of Contemporary Art, San Diego; Naropa Institute; Sun & Moon Press (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Series 6. Ephemera
  - Ephemera, 22 p. (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Includes flyers, announcements, posters (some involving Howe), curriculum vita, 3p.
- Series 7. Reviews and notices
  - Reviews and notices (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Includes 18 p. essay on Howe by Jean Day, with cover tls; plus 16 p. related material, including a few letters & xeroxes of letters